We're looking at the if statement, and we've seen how we can use multiple if statements to make evaluations.
But just looking at this, there's something suspiciously not 100% right here.
We mentioned that in our country the driving age is 18.
Now this is where there's the necessity for logic in your programming.
If you look at those two conditions we've got if age is less than or equal to 18, print.
Sorry, not old enough to drive.
And then if age is greater than 18 yes, you can drive.
Can you spot what is the problem if the official driving age in our country is 18?
Sarah, what's the problem?
Hopefully you did manage to spot it, but basically.
So everything runs perfectly fine.
But like my dad mentioned earlier, this is actually just a logical error.
So what we actually wanted is we wanted.
If my age is less than 18, we can't drive.
But if you are 18, you can.
So this should then become if my age is greater than or equal to 18.
So these logic errors are often trickier to find.
We've showed you if you mess up with the syntax of something, it's going to spot it.
So let's say for example we we forgot to put in the inverted commas there.
We run it.
And immediately we can see at the bottom here syntax error.
And it's telling you things are wrong.
Computers can help you with those sort of things.
The trick is getting your logic right.
And that's very important.
That's what's exciting about learning to program is you need to be logical.
And so you need to think about it.
And we'll look at later in debugging how you can try and solve some of these problems because they're
not always that easy to spot.
But that's part of the fun.
Okay, so now that we've fixed that logical error, let's just make this program a little bit more generic
generic.
So the thing about programming is you want to try.
And the reason we use variables and things like that is so our programs can always be reusable.
And we don't have to rewrite the same code over and over again.
So now instead of as you might have noticed here, we've written, if age is less than 18 here, and
then we wrote if age is greater than or equal to 18.
Yeah.
So instead of typing it out there twice and giving the chances that we might somehow mess this up.
If I had now said 19, then again, my logic is wrong.
So instead of doing that, let's rather create a variable that stores the driving age limit.
And what's good about this is that now we can use this variable and we only have to make a change in
one place.
So we're going to set the driving age limit here to 18.
So instead of now putting the number 18 here we're going to put in the variable.
So this is much more efficient use of coding because now we have one variable which is age limit.
And we can use it multiple times.
And so yes you can drive.
Now we can change that age limit in one place.
So maybe your age limit is 21 or whatever it might be in your country.
And we can very quickly run the same program and see whether it works.
So here the age is 15.
Run it.
Yes.
Okay.
If you're 19, you certainly can drive.
So that's basically also just showing you that you can compare two variables.
The second um party does not have to be a number.
It can be a variable.
And later we'll also look at other things or other data types that can be as well.
But for now we are going to look at else statements.
So before I mentioned that it's not really a good idea to write a whole lot of if statements like this
because there's a better way of doing it.
Okay, so the reason why we want to use an else statement, which is here we'll have a look at in a
moment, is the way that programs execute is from the top to the bottom of it already explained.
And they're going to do every single line.
The only place it's going to do a skip is if a condition is not true.
For example, here, if my age is less than age limit and that condition is not true, it will skip
that piece of code or those two lines and then jump to the next one.
Now, if you've got multiple if statements like we've got here on line three, line six, etc., your
program has to go through all of that.
It might not seem like a big deal, but as you get bigger and bigger programs, that slows it down.
And if you're trying to maybe write a game or write something that needs better performance.
All of that counts.
So it's very inefficient way of coding.
What we actually want is if this condition is true, it must do that and then ignore the other parts
of the condition, which is called the else part.
Alternatively, if this condition is not true, ignore that and then run the true part.
And so that's what an else does.
So rather than what we've got here in F has to be evaluated.
Then evaluate another f.
We're going to change this to an if and an else and will only evaluate one portion of this thereby making
it more efficient.
So let's give an example of an else statement.
Else statements are actually very, very simple to use.
All you need to know is how to tap that.
And that's a null statement.
It doesn't have any condition.
Because basically what else means is if everything above this else statement is false, then print this.
So it's only condition is that all the if statements above it were false.
So now what we wanted to do is first check if the age was less than the age limit.
Else if the age is not less than the age limit, then obviously the person must be able to drive.
So let's just print that statement again.
Print.
Okay, so this will do exactly what we had before.
And it is seen okay 19 is age.
The age limit is 15 is 19 days and 15.
No.
So then it goes straight to the else and prints this over here.
And again if I change this to less than the driving age limit, it's checked that and said oh yes that's
true.
And it's printed that.
But what's been efficient now is you can't see this, but it hasn't actually even looked at this part
here.
So while we're not seeing it or the performance gains here, this is how you must code.
It is much more effective.
And we're trying to teach you good habits up front.
So don't use multiple if statements if it's possible for you to use an else statement.